There are two things people keep asking
me about the SpaceX IPO. Will it get
added to their index funds and if given
the opportunity should they invest
directly in the IPO? Many of the major
indices have made changes to their rules
recently and it has a lot of people
confused but what's actually going to
happen when SpaceX goes public. If
keeping up with all these changes has
you a little confused about what this
all could mean for your portfolio, this
video is for you. I'm Ben Felix, Chief
Investment Officer at PWL Capital and
I'm going to tell you which index funds
will be buying SpaceX and when and why
SpaceX really wants you to invest in
their IPO.
The SpaceX IPO is expected to be by far
the largest IPO in history measured by
the amount of capital the company raises
and only Saudi Aramco comes close in
terms of total market cap at the time of
IPO. To pull this off the way that
SpaceX wants to, the company needs to
convince a lot of investors to buy its
shares. They've been pushing for two
things. Rule changes that will allow
near immediate inclusion in major stock
market indices and heavy retail investor
participation in the IPO. They've said
they want to allocate around 30% to
retail investors while a typical IPO
allocates 5 to 10% to retail. The
company has been largely successful with
these initiatives with many index
providers changing their rules and
retail brokerages promoting direct
investment in the SpaceX IPO to their
customers resulting in what looks like
it will be an oversubscribed IPO meaning
more people want to buy shares than
there are shares available. Let's go
through each of these issues to
understand the implications for you. One
of the biggest stories in finance
recently has been major indices changing
their rules leading up to the SpaceX IPO
and other large IPOs that are expected
to follow. Every index needs rules for
how to deal with new companies entering
the market through IPOs and market
changes in general. This is not a new
problem. Indices have rules to limit
when new stocks can enter and to filter
out stocks with certain characteristics.
For example, companies with a low free
float, that's a low proportion of total
shares that are freely available for
trading, would often be excluded from
indexes. Many indices also have or had
something like a waiting period before
new IPOs could get included. Stock
market indices are supposed to be
rules-based representations of parts of
the stock market or in some cases the
whole stock market.
nature has earned index funds, which
simply track the stocks in an index, the
title of passive. Passive makes it seem
like there aren't any decisions that
need to be made, but stock markets
themselves change and indices can change
their rules, which calls into question
how passive they really are. SpaceX
really wants to get added to stock
indices sooner than later, likely
because index funds mechanically buy the
stocks in the index, supporting the
stock's price. Stocks that qualify for
immediate index inclusion following
their IPO tend to see a jump in their
price leading up to index inclusion. To
be clear, index providers changing the
rules is not a bad thing. It's not
nefarious necessarily. The job of an
index is to represent the stock market.
If the market has changed, for example,
with larger than ever before companies
going public, it might make sense to
update the rules. That started happening
in February when Nasdaq, who runs the
Nasdaq 100 index, opened up a
consultation about potentially changing
the rules for IPO inclusion. FTSE
Russell followed suit and then S&P did
the same. These index providers together
dictate how trillions of dollars of
index fund assets are invested, so any,
even small, potential change has
sweeping implications for financial
markets in general and index fund
investors in particular. Nasdaq did
adopt changes in the end as did FTSE
Russell. I'll explain what changed and
what it means for investors in a minute.
In a move that surprised everyone, S&P
opted not to make changes to the S&P 500
and some of its other flagship indices
meaning that SpaceX won't be eligible
for inclusion until it's been trading
for 12 months.
Let's go through some major indices and
think about the implications of these
changes. The Nasdaq 100 is to quote
Nasdaq a globally recognized index of
100 of the most innovative large cap
companies listed on the Nasdaq stock
market.
The index is designed to track the 100
largest non-financial companies listed
on the Nasdaq exchange. It's not common
for a newly listed company to meet those
criteria, but SpaceX will. Nasdaq's
proposal explained that new constituents
can be added at reconstitution, which
happens once a year in December for that
index, or as replacements, which leads
to large newly listed companies often
being delayed from index inclusion
creating a gap between investor
expectations
and index market representation. Nasdaq
also had a three-month seasoning period
meaning that at a minimum a company had
to be trading for 3 months to be
included. Basically, if the index is
supposed to represent 100 of the most
innovative large cap companies listed on
the Nasdaq stock market, it should
probably include a company like SpaceX
sooner than later, but the existing
inclusion mechanisms before the changes
would have required a potentially long
delay. The proposed solution, which has
now been adopted, was to allow inclusion
after the 15th day of trading for stocks
that rank in the top 40 by total market
cap. So, for Nasdaq indices, we can
expect stocks like SpaceX, which satisfy
the inclusion criteria for the index, to
be added much sooner than the previous
rules would have allowed. The other
issue for Nasdaq was the 10% free float
requirement. If below 10% of the
company's shares were freely trading on
the stock market, they would not be
eligible. SpaceX is expected to have an
initial free float of 4%. Nasdaq
proposed and adopted removing the 10%
free float requirement, which is
interesting since it was only added in
June 2024. The other quirk here is that
unlike most indices, the Nasdaq 100 is
weighted by total market cap including
unlisted shares held by insiders, not
free float, which is what most indices
do. This means that while most indices
would weight SpaceX by its $75 billion
free float, the Nasdaq 100 would weight
it based on its roughly $1.8 trillion
total market cap. They recognized the
issue here for low float stocks in
particular, which may not have the
liquidity to support index inclusion at
total market cap. So, for low float
stocks, instead of using either the
total market cap like they normally do,
or the free float like most other
indices do, Nasdaq is using a cap of
three times the free float for stocks
with a low float. Combined, these
methodology changes mean that large
companies like SpaceX with a low float
can be added sooner, and once they're
included, held at a lower weight than
the previous methodology, but a higher
weight than most other float-weighted
indices.
Whether that's a good thing or not for
index fund returns remains to be seen,
but it's almost certainly a good thing
for SpaceX. Kind of like how subscribing
to this YouTube channel is almost
certainly a good thing for you. A lot of
people have been worried about these
fast inclusion changes from indices like
Nasdaq, but other major indices from
Crispr and MSCI have had fast inclusion
rules for years. Crispr, they run the
Crispr total market index behind
Vanguard's VTI ETF, allows fast track
inclusion entry after only five trading
days for eligible IPOs. Crispr did,
however, make a change to their free
float requirement for fast track entry.
It used to be 10% but was changed to 10%
or 0.005%
of the float-adjusted capitalization of
the index eligible universe, which was
$3.3 billion in in March 2026. This
quiet change, I mean, there wasn't a
consultation, there wasn't a big
announcement, allowed the index to
include companies like SpaceX, which
would have previously been excluded due
to its low free float. There's been a
lot of skepticism around changes like
this. Crisp, which was recently bought
by Morningstar, did a white paper
explaining the logic behind their
decisions and the implications of the
changes. Crisp explains that the updated
fast-track rules allow mega-cap IPOs
with a low float percentage, but a high
dollar float, to enter the index shortly
after they go public. They say that this
change allows Crisp market indexes to
reflect an opportunity set for a passive
investor without introducing additional
transaction costs. And they also say
that while float is an important
indicator for a typical IPO, it's less
informative for a very large company.
They also make the point that while
companies like SpaceX will be eligible
for inclusion in their indices, its
weight will be small due to the low free
float. Again, this is a float-weighted
index, unlike the Nasdaq 100. SpaceX,
for example, is estimated to make up 12
basis points, or 0.12%
of the Crisp US Total Market Index,
again, tracked by VTI and lots of other
funds. The big thing to watch for with
these IPOs is an increasing free float
over time as restrictions are lifted on
insiders. This is common for IPOs. For
example, at a 50% float, SpaceX would
make up 1.33%
of the index. It's worth calling out
another quirk of the SpaceX IPO here.
Rather than a traditional 180-day lockup
period for insiders, SpaceX has
provisions for the early release of
shares in stages. 20% of the restricted
shares can be sold after the second
trading day following their earnings
release. An additional 10% release
becomes available if the stock is
trading at least 30% above its offering
price for at least five of the 10
consecutive trading days ending on and
including the first earnings release
date. And additional blocks of 7% are
scheduled to become available 70, 90,
105, 120, and 135 days after the
listing. And another 28% becomes
available after their Q3 earnings
report. Then, after 180 days, any
remaining lockup shares will be
released. Back to Crisp, their analysis
concludes that Crisp indexes are
designed to capture the opportunity set
available to investors, not to select or
exclude companies based on assessments
of future viability. Crisp has always
had the leading index methodology here.
That's their words. With its fast-track
IPO methodology enabling newly listed
companies to enter the investor
opportunity set within 5 days.
That's a true statement, but there is
evidence that traders have been using
methodology to buy up shares leading up
to index inclusion, pushing the prices
higher followed by a drop after they're
included in the index, which is
effectively a cost on index fund
investors. MSCI has not made changes,
but they already had rules in place for
the fast-track inclusion of large IPOs
specifically. I think they're actually
throwing a bit of shade at other index
providers for making changes to
accommodate the upcoming high-profile
IPOs. Well, MSCI is like, we've been
doing this.
Good for them.
Their indices will include large IPOs
after 10 trading days as long as the
full market cap is at least 1.8 times
the market specific interim market size
segment cutoff or approximately 26
billion USD for the US market as of May
14th, 2026.
And the float-adjusted market cap is at
least 1.8 times 1/2 of the cutoff or
approximately USD 13 billion for the US
market as of May 14th, 2026. SpaceX
passes both of those tests. FTSE Russell
made a number of changes back in
February. The largest of these changes
was to include a fast entry rule for top
500 sized securities in an effort to
maintain better market representation.
Under the new rule for the FTSE Russell
US indices, eligible IPOs will be added
after the close of the fifth trading day
following the initial listing provided
they meet the minimum size requirement.
For the FTSE Russell US equity indices,
that requirement is an investable market
capitalization greater than the total
market capitalization breakpoint for the
Russell top 500 as of the previous
reconstitution. In other words, it needs
to be a top 500 company by market cap at
the time it goes public. If a company
has less than 5% of its shares freely
tradable, that's the the float issue,
because insiders are locked up, it can
still qualify as long as those lockups
expire within 12 months of being added
to the index, which would bring the
float above the minimum. SpaceX is
expected to satisfy this criteria based
on its S1 filing. That's the early
lockup releases that I mentioned
earlier. Lastly, we have S&P who have
gone in a completely different direction
than all the other indices, at least for
their flagship index, the S&P 500 and a
couple of others. Three major changes
were proposed to the S&P's inclusion
methodology, including reducing the IPO
seasoning period from 1 year down to 6
months, waving their investable weight
factor, which is basically a multiplier
to account for how much of a company's
shares are available to trade, that's
the float issue again, for mega cap
companies like SpaceX, and including a
financial viability exception for mega
cap companies, allowing these companies
to be included in the index without net
positive income. To all three of these
changes, S&P gave a resounding no. This
means that SpaceX could only enter the
S&P 500 around mid-2027 at the absolute
earliest, which assumes it becomes
profitable before then. S&P's total
market index does have fast track
inclusion. It it already did, and they
did adopt changes to eliminate the 10%
free float requirement for companies
ranked in the top 100 by total market
cap, so we should expect to see SpaceX
in this index. XTOT and ITOT, the US
equity ETFs in the iShares core equity
ETF portfolio, track this index. Okay,
we just covered a lot of indices, rules,
and rule changes. Here's a quick
breakdown of the relevant criteria and
whether each index is likely to include
SpaceX based on their published rules.
The implications of these changes are
meaningful, but it's important to keep
their significance in perspective. Index
funds tracking the indices with fast
track inclusion will be required to buy
SpaceX shares shortly after its IPO.
That buying is automatic and mandatory
for index funds. Their job is to track
the index. Index fund managers don't get
to decide whether SpaceX belongs in the
portfolio. If you're holding a broad
market index fund, you could very well
find yourself owning a piece of SpaceX
whether you chose to or not at whatever
price the market sets in the first 5,
10, or 15 days of trading depending on
the index we're talking about. But most
indices will only weight the stock based
on its free float or in the case of the
Nasdaq 100, three times its free float.
For context, 45% of VEQT, the Vanguard
All Equity ETF portfolio, is invested in
VUN, which tracks the Crisp US Total
Market Index. If SpaceX makes up 0.12%
of that index 5 days after the IPO, it
will make up 0.05%
of VEQT.
The other key feature of this IPO is the
retail allocation. SpaceX is looking to
raise an enormous amount of capital
directly from retail investors and
rather than the traditional book
building to figure out their IPO price,
they're reportedly taking the unusual
stance of setting their IPO price ahead
of time. Elon Musk has a long-running
relationship with retail investors who
have been very willing to buy shares in
his companies at high valuations based
on a belief in his vision. It's kind of
like buying an Elon Musk lottery ticket.
By allocating 30% of the IPO directly to
probably Elon-loving retail investors,
SpaceX can probably target a higher IPO
price. Fidelity lowered its typical
minimum of $100,000 and up for retail
investors to participate in IPOs down to
$2,000 for the SpaceX IPO. People have
sent me marketing emails from other
discount brokers promoting participation
in the IPO. Wealthsimple here in Canada
is also offering IPO access. Buying at
the IPO price has historically worked
out well, generally speaking. There's a
well-documented IPO pop where the value
of the company shares see a big price
jump from the IPO price to the price
investors on the public market are
willing to pay for the shares. One note
for people who hear that and think
they'll get in on the IPO and
immediately flip the shares, most
brokers have anti-flipping rules. For
example, Wealthsimple wants you to hold
the shares for 90 days or you lose
access to future IPOs. Fidelity wants
you to hold for 15 days or risk the same
fate. It's usually very difficult for
retail investors to get access to the
IPO price, which makes this all seem
compelling. But that's been changing as
access to retail investors has
increased. And it's not changing in a
good way. The 2025 paper Retail IPO
Access: High Hopes, Low Returns looked
at 24 IPOs that included retail investor
allotments through Robinhood and SoFi,
who are both involved with the retail
distribution for the SpaceX IPO. They
found that on average these retail IPO
stocks declined by over 60% from their
offer price after 1 year,
underperforming regular non-retail IPOs
that happened around the same time by 20
percentage points. The authors find two
potential explanations for this
underperformance. The first is adverse
selection. The issuers and underwriters
participate in retail IPOs at their own
discretion. They choose which shares
they're going to push on retail
investors, and evidence suggests that
they're more likely to do so when
pricing is more aggressive relative to
earnings, when they have high prices,
meaning that the less informed retail
investors are more easily able to get a
bigger cut of what turns out to be a bad
deal. Again, that's adverse selection.
This creates something known as the
winner's curse. The winner who receives
a large allocation has paradoxically won
something they probably didn't want.
This explanation is somewhat incomplete
though, because although retail
investors were more likely to be offered
aggressively priced deals, the typical
retail allocation was only 2% of shares
in this analysis, which is too small a
share to suggest that retail was simply
being used as a dumping ground for deals
institutions didn't want. If the goal
was just to dump bad deals on retail
investors, why would they give them such
a small slice? Adverse selection helps
explain which deals end up in front of
retail investors, but it doesn't fully
explain the price dynamics that follow.
For that, we need to look at the second
explanation that the paper offers,
attention-driven trading. The brokers
offering retail IPOs sent push
notifications and emails about upcoming
IPOs to their millions of users about 9
days prior to the IPO on average. And
again, I'm hearing the same thing is
happening now. I don't personally have a
discount broker account, but
apparently this is happening. Google
search interest for retail IPO tickers
in this study saw a sharp spike in the 6
to 10 days before trading, matching the
notification timing almost exactly,
while comparable IPOs that were not part
of these programs pushed on retail
investors showed no equivalent surge in
interest. When trading opened, Robinhood
users placed roughly 11 to 13 times more
fractional trades in retail IPO stocks
than in comparable IPOs on the first day
of trading. This buying frenzy
temporarily inflated prices, but as that
attention faded and buying pressure
dissipated, prices fell. Crucially, when
the authors controlled for first day of
retail trading volume in their models,
the underperformance gap became
statistically indistinguishable from
zero, suggesting that this attention
mechanism accounts for a significant
portion of why these stocks perform so
poorly after the IPO. The combined
result is a pattern cleanly summarized
by an institutional investor quoted in
the paper. If a retail investor can get
an IPO allocation, they don't want it.
Which brings us back to Space X. I can't
tell you whether you should request a
Space X IPO allocation from your broker,
but the historical data on a retail IPO
access suggests that it might be a bumpy
ride. That said, Elon's fans have a
track record of pumping Elon's
companies. There's really no way to say
where this one will go, but caution is
warranted. I am not predicting a price
drop, to be clear, so don't tell me a
year from now that this video didn't age
well.
All I'm saying is that it's worth being
careful, which hopefully all of you
know. Most major stock indices will
likely include SpaceX shares within days
after the IPO, but at allocations that
shouldn't matter too much. One flagship
index that has not changed its rules is
the S&P 500, which is also the index
with by far the most assets tracking it.
This combined with SpaceX's aggressive
lockup release plan will make for some
potentially interesting performance
divergence between the S&P 500 and other
US stock market indices. In any case,
all these changes highlight the fact
that indexing isn't as passive as we
like to think. The funny thing is that
well active management has gotten a bad
name for good reason. There are actively
managed funds that share all the
positive attributes of index funds like
low fees and broad diversification, but
have the discretion to decide whether to
invest in IPOs. Two examples are
Dimensional Fund Advisors, whose funds
my firm PWL Capital uses, and Avantis,
who just launched ETFs in Canada that I
covered in a recent video.